<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>All the letters, memorials, and considerations concerning the offered alliance of the kings of England and France to the high and mighty Lords the states of the United Neatherlands, according to the several times when they were delivered with considerations on the said alliance and also reflections on the said considerations / faithfully translated from the Dutch copies printed at Haerlem by Barent Jansen...</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 58 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A26671</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A943</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10192</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13289839</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13289839</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98825</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A26671)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98825)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 444:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>All the letters, memorials, and considerations concerning the offered alliance of the kings of England and France to the high and mighty Lords the states of the United Neatherlands, according to the several times when they were delivered with considerations on the said alliance and also reflections on the said considerations / faithfully translated from the Dutch copies printed at Haerlem by Barent Jansen...</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>11 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Robert Harford ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Netherlands --  History --  1648-1714 --  Sources.</term>
               <term>Netherlands --  Politics and government --  1648-1714 --  Sources.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98825:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98825:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ALL THE Letters, Memorials, AND CONSIDERATIONS, Concerning the offered ALLIANCE Of the KINGS of <hi>England and France,</hi> TO THE High and Mighty LORDS, THE STATES OF THE UNITED NEATHERLANDS, According to the ſeveral Times when they were delivered: With Conſiderations on the ſaid ALLIANCE, and alſo Reflections on the ſaid CONSIDERATIONS. <hi>Faithfully Tranſlated from the</hi> Dutch <hi>Copies printed at</hi> Haerlem <hi>by</hi> Barent Janſen, <hi>Hoog Euys,</hi> 1680.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Harford,</hi> at the <hi>Angel</hi> in <hi>Cornhill,</hi> near the <hi>Royal-Exchange,</hi> 1680.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:98825:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98825:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The Heer Ambaſſadour <hi>Boreel,</hi> to Pentioner <hi>Fagell.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt Honourable and Noble Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>HAving been lately to viſit the Marqueſs, <hi>de Louvois,</hi> who keeps his bed of a broken Leg, we had ſome diſcourſe together, of the nature whereof, I thought it fit to give your Honour an account, that you may thereby take your meaſures, if it do afford any matter that concerns the public. After ſome general diſcourſes about ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral occurrences, his Honour told me, That it was a matter of wonder, that the Peace betwixt the King and the States being concluded above a year ago, and we having for nine Months reſided at Court, yet there was not the leaſt inclination diſcovered on the part of the States, to enter into a nearer Alliance with the King; but on the contrary, it was taken notice of, that in <hi>Holland</hi> Leagues and Confederacies were ſought for elſewhere: Adding farther, That they had been acquainted by the by with an earneſt Letter from the Elector of <hi>Brandenburgh</hi> to the States, ſince the Peace was concluded with <hi>Sweden,</hi> by the mediation of the King; and likewiſe with the manner how <hi>Spain</hi> demanded the reſtitution of <hi>Maeſtricht;</hi> threatning. That they would ſeize the <hi>Dutch</hi> effects which were expected in the Gallions, in caſe the aforeſaid City were not deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered up to that King. Such and the like accidents (continued he) do happen to the State, and are like to be attended with worſe, if they continue without making Alliances with other Princes. And what think you (ſaid he) if the King and this Kingdom were in League with you as formerly? It is well known with what Succours His Majeſty was then obliged to aſſiſt the States, in caſe they ſhould be attacqued. I do not affirm for a certain truth (added he) that <hi>Spain</hi> will proceed to repriſal, upon the effects of the <hi>Hollanders;</hi> but all our advices from <hi>Madrid</hi> tell us, that that Court was reſolved ſo to do. Hereupon I aſſured his Honour, That their High and Mightineſſes did highly honour the King his Maſter's friendſhip, and would uſe their greateſt care to entertain it, and endeavour to live in a good correſpondence with His Majeſty and his Subjects, by contributing to the utmoſt what lay in their power, for the preſervation of the ſame. That we had expreſs Orders from their High and Mightineſſes to aſſure His Majeſty, that there was no ſuch thing as a League, that was talked of, with <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Spain;</hi> but that their High and Mightineſſes would obſerve the Treaties which they had made with His Majeſty, and therefore had not as yet, nor intended not to enter into any Alliance, which might prove inconſiſtent with the concluded Peace. To this the Marqueſs <hi>de Louvois</hi> did reply, That that was well; but yet that there appeared in all this no inclination on the part of the States to a nearer Alliance with his Maſter, though he could aver, that His Majeſty
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:98825:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>was fully inclined to it: That it was not reaſonable to expect overtures from him; but notwithſtanding, if it were perceived that the States ſeemed indifferent in that point, the ſame perhaps might be done with others, who did ſhew a greater inclination to the thing: And if ſo (ſaid he) what the intereſt of your Country will be, the iſſue will diſcover. To conclude, having again as formerly aſſured his Honour of the ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the States, I took my leave. Moſt honourable and noble Lord, I communicated the ſubſtance of this Conference to the Lord <hi>Dyckveld;</hi> but his Excellency not thinking it fit to write a particular, which happened to me alone, though it be not pleaſing to their High and Mightineſſes that we ſhould ſingly write to the Penſioner, yet I thought it my duty to acquaint your Honour with what I ſo unexpectedly met with; for what I know of the humour of that Lord, ſuch free diſcourſes as theſe are not without Deſign But this I ſubmit to your Honours known wiſdom, and beg leave in compliance with my Duty to write my ſelf.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Paris,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Auguſt</hi> 25. 1679.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Jacob Boreel.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <opener>
               <dateline>Paris, <date>September <hi>1. 1679.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE Marqueſs of <hi>Louvois</hi> being ſo much recovered from the indiſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, which happened to him above a Month ago by a fall from his Horſe, as to admit of viſits. Laſt week the <hi>Heer Boreel</hi> went to wait upon him, where, amongſt other things, he told his Excellency, that he wondered that the Peace betwixt this Kingdom and the States, being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded above a year ago, and their Ambaſſadours having reſided at this Court eight or nine Months, there ſhould be no mention, nor propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion made on the part of their High and Mightineſſes, of entering into a nearer Alliance with this Crown, when Leagues were ſolicited at other places, which he was aſſured would not prove ſucceſsful. That there had been a Letter of the Elector of <hi>Brandenburgh</hi> communicated to him, which was written to the States upon the ſubject of the Peace, that was concluded betwixt him and <hi>Sweden</hi> by the mediation of the King: As likewiſe the Memorial by way of Anſwer, which was preſented by the Lord <hi>Delira</hi> to the Aſſembly of their High and Mightineſſes, concerning the giving up of the City of <hi>Maeſtricht.</hi> In both which, the demands were urged in very preſſing terms, and eſpecially in the laſt, which threatned repriſal on the Effects that the <hi>Dutch</hi> Merchants expect in the Gallions. That his Honour could not ſay poſitively that that would be put in execution, but that all the Letters from <hi>Madrid</hi> gave ſuch advice. And that theſe and ſuch-like occurrences, which perhaps might be fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed with worſe, were only occaſioned by the States, remaining without particular Alliances with other Kings. That his Honour thought he might aſſure us, that we needed not fear any ſuch accidents, in caſe the States
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:98825:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>were allied with the King his Maſter, and this Kingdom, it being well known with what ſuccours they would be aſſiſted by this King againſt thoſe that ſhould attack them. Being anſwered to this, that their High and Mightineſſes did highly value the honour of His Majeſty's friendſhip, and that it would be their conſtant endeavours to preſerve the ſame. That they would contribute what in them lay, to live with the King and his Subjects in amity and good correſpondence; and that as an inſtance there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, it was not long ſince by expreſs Orders from their High and Mighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, they had aſſured Monſieur <hi>Pomponne</hi> of the ſincerity of the States, and that there was not only nothing in the pretended League with <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Spain;</hi> but alſo that their High and Mightineſſes would punctually obſerve the Treaties which they had made with His Majeſty, and that conſequently they had not made, neither would they make any Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which might be prejudicial to the Amity of His Majeſty, and Peace concluded with him. Monſieur <hi>Louvois</hi> did hereupon reply, That this was all well; but notwithſtanding it did not hereby appear, that the States had any inclination to engage in a nearer Alliance: That his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour could aſſure us both, that the King was inclined to it, but that it could not be expected that His Majeſty ſhould make the firſt overtures. Farther adding, That if it were obſerved, that the States ſeemed indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent as to the thing, meaſures might be taken here for doing the ſame thing with others, who ſhew themſelves more inclinable that way, the iſſue whereof would inform us, whether that would be for the intereſt of our Country, or not. The Heer <hi>Dyckvelt</hi> having ſince waited on Monſieur <hi>Louvois,</hi> to congratulate with him upon his recovery, and the Marriage of his Daughter to the Prince of <hi>Rocheguyon,</hi> eldeſt Son of the Prince of <hi>Mallſillarq,</hi> Maſter of the Robes to His Majeſty, and chief Huntſman of the Grown. After ſome mutual Compliments upon occaſion of the viſit, and ſome diſcourſes concerning the Times, Monſieur <hi>Louvois</hi> ſtarted the ſame ſubject, which he had ſpoken of before to the Heer <hi>Boreel,</hi> repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the ſubſtance of the afore-mentioned diſcourſe: And having pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted, that what he ſaid was without any Orders, and that he ſpoke but as one Friend to another. He told him, That the King was fully inclined to enter into a new Alliance with the States, but that His Majeſty muſt be thereunto requeſted; and that the ſincerity of his intentions might be manifeſt, he was willing to condeſcend to advantagious Conditions: That there being no contrary intereſt as to the matter of Commerce betwixt the States and this Kingdom, their High and Mightineſſes would find their advantage in a nearer Alliance; that the ſame would conduce to the ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the common Barrier: And that the <hi>Spaniſh Neatherlands</hi> might never fall into the hands of the <hi>French,</hi> it might be ſtipulated with ſuch neceſſary conditions and caution as ſhould be demanded. Adding far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that for inſtance, the King would probably engage himſelf never to attack theſe Countries; and that if at any time he ſhould enter into a War with <hi>Spain,</hi> he ſhould not act in theſe Quarters, much leſs make himſelf by Arms or Treaties Maſter of the ſmalleſt Cottage therein. That he ſhould not poſſeſs the <hi>Neatherlands,</hi> either by ſale or voluntary reſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and if he ſhould, that in that caſe the Alliance ſhould be broken, and their High and Mightineſſes at liberty to joyn in League with any
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:98825:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>other Prince or Potentate. His Honour added farther, That if the King were forced to attack <hi>Spain</hi> ſomewhere elſe, what projudice would it be to their High and Mightineſſes, if His Majeſty ſhould make a Conqueſt of the <hi>Milanois,</hi> or ſome part on the Frontiers of <hi>Spain?</hi> Beſides, (ſaid he) put the queſtion we ſhould ſhortly break with <hi>Spain,</hi> becauſe of the Orders that are ſent to <hi>Vivonne,</hi> to make the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Ships and Gallions ſtrike, would it be for the intereſt of the States to renew the War with us? To this, and the conditions propoſed, a civil Anſwer was made to Monſieur <hi>Louvois,</hi> as the Heer <hi>Boreel</hi> had done before, affuring his Honour, That the intentions of the States were ſincere, and that they would endeavour religiouſly to obſerve the Peace, to live with His Majeſty in good Intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, and true Amity, and to do all they could to cultivate the ſame, and make it durable.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Signed, <hi>Jacob Boreel,</hi> &amp; <hi>Dyckvelt.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="memorandum">
            <head>The Memorial preſented by the <hi>French</hi> Ambaſſadour to the States of the <hi>United Provinces, Jan. 8. 1680.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>MOnſieur <hi>d'Avaux</hi> has received an Expreſs, with new and preciſe Orders to repreſent to their High and Mightineſſes, that the King his Maſter does wiſh that they would once declare themſelves, and the rather, that after mutual Embaſſies, His Majeſty cannot doubt, but that their High and Mightineſſes are ſatisfied that it is his intention to make a ſtrict Alliance with them; and ſince there remains no conſiderable difficulty to hinder the concluſion thereof, His Majeſty is perſuaded that all delays are but excuſes; for it is not juſt, that after ſo full a knowledge of his ſentiments, His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty ſhould not be preciſely informed of your reſolutions: And ſeeing His Majeſty cannot have the ſame aſſurance of your friendſhip, as he is willing to give you of his, the ſaid Ambaſſadour thinks himſelf obliged to deſire their High and Mightineſſes, that they would make a ſerious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flexion upon this, as upon many other affairs, which may tend to the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing of a defenſive and laſting Alliance, and public friendſhip with His Majeſty. And laſtly, that His Majeſty may be ſpeedily informed of their intentions, that he may take his meaſures accordingly, and act as their High and Mightineſſes ſhall be pleaſed to demean themſelves towards him.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Given at the <hi>Hague</hi> 
                  <date>the <hi>18th</hi> of <hi>January,</hi> 1680.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="memorandum">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:98825:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The Memorial of Mr. <hi>Sidney,</hi> Envoy extraordinary of the King of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> to the States of the <hi>United Provinces,</hi> on <hi>Jan. 9. 1680.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE Envoy extraordinary of the King of <hi>Great Britain</hi> makes no doubt, but that your High and Mightineſſes are fully informed by your Ambaſſadours at the Court of <hi>England,</hi> what pains the Moſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian King takes, to draw you into a nearer Alliance for mutual deſence, with His Majeſty: And becauſe the Ambaſſadour of his Moſt Chriſtian Majeſty did by his Memorial of yeſterday propoſe the ſame to your High and Mightineſſes; the Envoy having expreſs Orders from the King his Maſter, does repreſent to your High and Mightineſſes, that his Maſter cannot look upon the aforeſaid Alliance otherwiſe than as a confederacy againſt him, and the rather, becauſe your High and Mightineſſes have refuſed to paſs an Act of <hi>Guarantee</hi> of the laſt Treaties of Peace at <hi>Nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meghen,</hi> to which he had obliged you by two ſeveral Trearies of the <hi>10th</hi> of <hi>January,</hi> and the <hi>26th</hi> of <hi>July,</hi> 1678. That the King his Maſter concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, that this Alliance meant no leſs than the <hi>French</hi> King's giving Rules to this State. But that His Majeſty being in full Peace, and no ways apprehenſive of his neighbouring Princes, and your High and Mighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes being likewiſe in no danger of being in the leaſt moleſted by any, by a nearer Alliance with you, His Majeſty has no other aim, but that he may not give the <hi>French</hi> King an occaſion of ſhewing his diſpleaſure for the ſeparate Peace, which His Majeſty made with your High and Mightineſſes, in the year 1674.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="memorandum">
            <head>The Memorial preſented by the <hi>French</hi> Ambaſſadour to the States General, <hi>January 12. 1680.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE Count <hi>d'Avaux,</hi> Ambaſſadour extraordinary of his Moſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Majeſty, by a Memorial preſented to your High and Mighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes the <hi>8th</hi> inſtant, ſignified to you the intentions of the King his Maſter, concerning an Alliance propounded betwixt His Majeſty and this State; and having as yet no Anſwer, he cannot longer delay his Obedience to the preciſe Orders of His Majeſty, by letting your High and Mightineſſes know, that be much wondred that you ſhould put off to another time the concluſion of this Alliance. That His Majeſty would have been pleaſed, and taken it well, if, without urging the matter, your High and Mightineſſes had ſent a ſolemn Embaſſy to deſire that favour of him, eſpecially having concluded a Peace with you, and given you by word and deeds ſo many proofs of his ſincere friendſhip, and promiſed to be true to it; it is therefore His Majeſty's deſire, that your High and Mighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:98825:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>would ſhew a reciprocal procedure, and carry your ſelves as you have done, nor only to former Kings, but to His Majeſty himſelf; for ſince the Eſtabliſhment of your High and Mightineſſes States, you have conſtantly deſired of His Majeſty's Predeceſſors and himſelf, the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of their Alliance and Protection, which was ſignally manifeſted in the year 1648, when His Majeſty's Forces joyned with yours, procured your High and Mightineſſes a firm and ſetled Peace; ſince which time you have ſeveral times with inſtances ſollicited the renewing of that old Alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance and Friendſhip: And namely, in the year 1662, you ſent a ſolemn Embaſſy to His Majeſty to deſire an Alliance, which then was granted and concluded. That the Alliance propoſed by His Majeſty is no more but the renewing of former Leagues, and is purely defenſive, having no other regard, but the maintaining of your High and Mightineſſes State in a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Peace, and freedom of Commerce, without any danger or fear, and no deſign to involve the States in new troubles, but to confirm a general Peace in all <hi>Europe.</hi> And this being the only reaſon why His Majeſty applies himſelf to you at this time, and that your High and Mightineſſes may have the ſame Alliance with ſeveral other Princes and States: It could not enter into His Majeſty's thoughts, after he has given you ſo many De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrations of his ſincere friendſhip, that the renewing of this Alliance ſhould meet with any difficulty or oppoſition, and that two Months ſhould be expired, without having as yet received from you any final Reſolution. That His Majeſty could not perſuade himſelf, that the Declaration of the King of <hi>England</hi> ſhould make any impreſſion on the minds of your High and Mightineſſes, ſeeing the League offered by <hi>England</hi> is wholly offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive as deſigned againſt His Majeſty, when the Alliance which he propoſes can be of no ill conſequence to the King of <hi>England,</hi> if he will continue in Peace, and not attack the States, as he did in the year 1665; for then His Majeſty would be obliged to defend them, as he did at that time. And in regard the Alliance which His Majeſty propoſes will do good to all, and injure no perſon, the preſent Declaration of the King of <hi>England</hi> againſt it, ought to be of leſs force than that which the ſame Prince made to His Majeſty in the year 1662, to hinder the Alliance which he then made with your High and Mightineſſes, and particularly to hinder his being <hi>Guarantee</hi> in an Affair which himſelf intended to diſturb. And ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing His Majeſty let ſlip no occaſion of ſhewing his good will to the States, and eſpecially at ſo important a juncture as this is, His Majeſty may juſtly conclude, that your High and Mightineſſes will have no regard to a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration that has ſo little ground for it; but that you will now call to mind the many demonſtrations of His Majeſty's true and faithful Amity, particularly that helpful Tax of <hi>Tariff,</hi> in the year 1664, which is of great advantage to your Traffic, when he deſires only the renewing of the Treaty of the year 1662, which is purely defenſive, of the ſame nature with thoſe that your High and Mightineſſes have concluded with other Princes and States, and of great advantage for ſecuting your fiſhing Trade. His Majeſty has likewiſe ordered the Ambaſſadour to acquaint your High and Mightineſſes, that if you delay the renewing of the ſaid Alliance, he will look upon it as a refuſal to engage in ſo ſincere friendſhip and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence, as he would do with you, and at a time when the forbearing
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:98825:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>of it may be of hurtful conſequence; as on the contrary, the concluding thereof cannot but tend to the ſetling of your State in Peace, and the increaſe of your Trade and Greatneſs, and at ſuch a time alſo, when His Majeſty relies not upon your High and Mightineſſes for Peace and ſecurity at home. That he knows there is a party among you which do not favour His Majeſty; but that ye might be aſſured the King would take the ſame meaſures with them, and that he will employ all his power for promoting of Commerce among his own Subjects, whereſoever it can be done. His Majeſty has made his intentions to this effect known to the Ambaſſadours of your High and Mightineſſes, and willed them to communicate the ſame to you, and that he deſires a poſitive Anſwer within 15 days; after which time His Majeſty's Ambaſſadour is ordered to ſollicit the matter no more, His Majeſty being reſolved to obſerve the ſame meaſures as your High and Mightineſſes have done with him.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Given at the <hi>Hague</hi> 
                  <date>the twelfth of <hi>January,</hi> 1680.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>A Copy of the Earl of <hi>Sunderland</hi>'s Letter to Mr. <hi>Sidney,</hi> Envoy extraordinary from His Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> to the States of the <hi>United Provinces,</hi> dated <hi>January 14. 1680.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>VVHen I had read your Letter in Council, I had Orders to ſpeak with the Heer <hi>Van Leuwen,</hi> concerning the Alliance propoſed by <hi>France</hi> to the States. I told him, That the King would take it ill, if his Maſters ſhould come to a concluſion with <hi>France,</hi> after they had refuſed ſuch an Alliance as they themſelves had formerly deſired of His Majeſty, and ſent Ambaſſadours to treat about the ſame. I told him alſo, That if the States ſhould take that courſe, this defenſive Alliance might hereafter oblige them to other meaſures with <hi>France;</hi> and if the <hi>French</hi> King ſhould enter into a War, they would find themſelves thereby neceſſitated to aſſiſt that Crown, which would be ſufficient cauſe of a breach betwixt <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Holland.</hi> His Majeſty (I told him) did intend to tell him ſo himſelf, and therefore deſired to ſpeak with him. His Anſwer was, That he would acquaint his Maſters with it, and that he did not believe they would accept the Propoſals of Monſieur <hi>d'Avaux.</hi> In a word, you muſt uſe your utmoſt endeavours to hinder this Alliance, and aſſure the States, That His Majeſty will do any thing that is reaſonable; not doubting, but that he, with the aſſiſtance of the States of <hi>Holland,</hi> is in a condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of preſerving the quiet and peace of <hi>Europe,</hi> which is both their intereſts.</p>
            <div type="postscript">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:98825:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>The Earl of <hi>Sunderland</hi>'s Poſtcript, with his own hand.</head>
               <p>YOU muſt preſs this Affair to the States as much as poſſible you can, and ſhew them the ill conſequences of ſuch an Alliance; for if it take effect, His Majeſty may be moved to take other meaſures, though it is againſt his inclination.</p>
               <closer>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Jan.</hi> 14. 1680.</date>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Paris,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>January</hi> 15. 1680.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>YEſterday evening, being <hi>Sunday,</hi> Monſieur <hi>Girault,</hi> Deputy Intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductor of Ambaſſadours, came to the houſe of us your High and Mightineſſes's Ambaſſadours, and in the name of Monſieur <hi>Golbert</hi> acquainted us, That we ſhould next day, about nine of the Clock, wait on His Majeſty at St. <hi>Germans.</hi> Accordingly we went thither this Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and betwixt ten and eleven were brought to an Audience in the Cloſet, where we found His Majeſty all alone, ſtanding by the Window. When we had made the accuſtomed Reverences to the King, His Majeſty was pleaſed to tell us, That he thought it convenient to ſignifie to us, that upon Concluſion of the laſt Peace, he had had a great inclination to re-eſtabliſh with their High and Mightineſſes, the ancient friendſhip and correſpondence that had been betwixt the Crown and the States General; and that therefore he had by his Miniſters, here to us, and his Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours to their High and Mightineſſes at the <hi>Hague,</hi> given intimation of his willingneſs to renew the former Alliance with them; but becauſe he is ſincere in the Affair, he did now declare the ſame himſelf, and confirm what ever Monſieur <hi>Colbert</hi> had told us concerning it. That the Alliance with his Crown had been very profitable and advantagious to the States, in the years 1665 and 1666, and the ſame in former times much deſired by them: That therefore he was much ſurpriſed to find ſuch delays in the States in the concluſion thereof, and thought fit, by an Expreſs this day, to order the Count <hi>d'Avaux</hi> to demand of their High and Mightineſſes a poſitive and final Reſolution concerning the propoſed Alliance, that His Majeſty might know what he was to expect from them, and accordingly take his meaſures for the good of his Subjects. His Majeſty deſired, That we ſhould, by an Expreſs, acquaint the States with what he had ſaid to us; or, That if we thought it convenient, His Majeſty's Courrier ſhould carry our Letters. We thereupon promiſed His Majeſty to write to your High and Mightineſſes, and give you a true account of what he told us, and ſo took our leaves.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:98825:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A Letter from the Ambaſſadours of the <hi>States Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral</hi> to their <hi>High</hi> and <hi>Mightineſſes.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <dateline>St. <hi>Germans,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>January</hi> 17. 1680.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>AFter we had yeſterday diſpatched the incloſed, to be ſent by the King's Expreſs to the Count <hi>d'Avaux;</hi> inſtead of the Expreſs, the Lord <hi>Bovin de Fes</hi> came to us, and told us, That we ſhould this day have Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the King, and that therefore we ſhould be at St. <hi>Germans</hi> by nine of the Clock in the Morning. At ten of the Clock we received by an Expreſs your High and Mightineſſes Commands, with your Reſolution of the twelfth inſtant. In purſuance of the notice given us, we came thither this Morning, and being introduced into the King's Cloſet, and received by him as we were yeſterday, His Majeſty was pleaſed to tell us, That ſince he had ſpoken to us yeſterday, he had received News from his Ambaſſadour at the <hi>Hague,</hi> and that Monſieur <hi>Colbert</hi> had received ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Letter from the ſaid Ambaſſadour, a little before the Expreſs of your High and Mightineſſes was ſent to us. That he found no reaſon to alter his thoughts, and therefore muſt tell us, That he was highly ſurpriſed, that your High and Mightineſſes, inſtead of profeſſing a ſatisfaction of entering into the Alliance offered by His Majeſty to the States, had only thought fit to make a Declaration, which does no ways content His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty; and that he had offered a defenſive Alliance, and therefore thought, that he ought to have a poſitive Reſolution to take his meaſures by. That His Majeſty would not threaten you with his indignation, as others did, but that he could not but declare unto us, That if your High and Migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſſes would not enter into the Alliance propoſed, he would conceive that the States had other deſigns, and that conſequently be obliged to confederate with other Princes and Potentates for the intereſt and welfare of his Subjects, and the encreaſing and encouraging of their Trade by all poſſible ways. That as ſoon as we were gone, he would ſend Orders to his Ambaſſadour <hi>d'Avaux</hi> to acquaint your High and Mightineſſes, that within ten days he expected a final Reſolution concerning the offered Alliance; and that if the ſame was not done within the limitted time, his Ambaſſadour ſhould ſtir no more in the matter, but that His Majeſty would forthwith reſolve and deport himſelf as ſhould beſt ſtand with his conveniency. Being anſwered by us, That we could aſſure His Majeſty; that your High and Mightineſſes thought themſelves highly obliged by the Honour ſhew'd the States in the offer of his friendſhip; and that though you could not for ſeveral weighty difficulties embrace the ſaid Alliance, yet you would always, and upon all occaſions, make appear, not only your ſincere intentions religiouſly and exactly to obſerve the peace, but like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:98825:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>the extraordinary value and eſteem you made of His Majeſty's friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and favours, and your earneſt endeavours to promote and cultivate the ſame by all lawful and becoming means; and that if this could pleaſe His Majeſty, we made no doubt, but that your High and Mightineſſes would give a public and ſatisfactory Declaration in this matter. The King replied, That the Penſionary has already declared as much to his Ambaffa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour, but that be could eaſily perceive, that the diſlike they had of the ſaid Alliance proceeded from the Conſideration they had for <hi>England;</hi> and that inſtead of an Alliance he could by no means take ſuch a Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to be ſatisfactory: And that His Majeſty having acquainted your High and Mightineſſes with his inclinations of renewing his ancient Friendſhip and League with the States, he expected that you would on your parts fully comply with him, and make an Alliance, which His Majeſty, by his Ambaſſadours, had propoſed to your High and Mightineſſes. He farther deſired us, That we would give your High and Mightineſſes as full and exact an account of this Affair as poſſibly we could, becauſe His Majeſty had been informed, That we had not been ſo punctual in our former Letters, in relating what Monſieur <hi>Colbert</hi> had acquainted us with; and thereupon His Majeſty would have diſmiſſed us: But we took the freedom, firſt, to excuſe our ſelves concerning the aforeſaid report, proteſting, that we had omitted nothing in our Letters to your High and Mightineſſes, of what Monſieur <hi>Colbert</hi> had propoſed to us; and then added, That a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive Alliance contained commonly but three principal Points; the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of Amity and Peace; the not engaging in War the one againſt the other; and in caſe of an attack, to give Succours. That we could aſſure His Majeſty, That your High and Mightineſſes are willing to grant the two firſt, and upon that head declare your ſelves to His Majeſty's ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, and that the laſt was no way advantagious for him, being ſo powerful; but on the contrary, of great advantage to the States, our Republic being ſo low at preſent; that His Majeſty would therefore be pleaſed to think, that the reaſons muſt be very weighty that hinder'd the States to embrace the laſt, which would be ſo much to their advantage; and that we, in the name of your High and Mightineſſes, could declare, that the obſtacle was not grounded upon the Propoſals of the King of <hi>England.</hi> Not withſtanding His Majeſty perſiſted in his former ſentiments, and repeated his fore-mentioned Arguments, telling us, That if we pleaſed to ſee Monſieur <hi>Colbert,</hi> he would more fully explain to us His Majeſty's meaning. Having accordingly in the Afternoon gone to wait on Monſieur <hi>Colbert,</hi> his Excellency, more amply and in higher terms, urged but the ſame thing that His Majeſty had done: And we making uſe of the Reaſons alleaged for the reſolution of the States, and what others at that time oecurred to us, endeavoured to perſuade him, That His Majeſty ſhould adhere to the former Treaties; that nothing was more the reſolution and intention of your High and Mightineſſes, than to give to His Majeſty what contentment poſſibly you could: And that for His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's ſatisfaction, your High and Mightineſſes would paſs a Declaration, containing the two principal Points of a defenſive Alliance, without any Article of giving mutual Aſſiſtance to each other, by which the greateſt advantage would redound to your High and Mightineſſes; and that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:98825:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>it was evident, that the difficulties which hindred your High and Mightineſſes were of the greateſt moment and inſuperable. To this his Excellency made anſwer, that he did confeſs he underſtood our Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but that the more force there was in it, the more it made for the King; that by their way of proceeding which was never uſed in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of Treaties, ſomething of conſequence muſt be concealed; for it could not well be conceived that your High and Mightineſſes ſhould give a Declaration that ſhould be ſatisfactory to his Majeſty, and be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs unwilling to enter into an Alliance, which in regard it would contain more than the aforeſaid two Articles, namely, the giving of mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual ſuccours, muſt of neceſſity be more to the advantage of the States, than of his Majeſty; that therefore it was to be believed, that the diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties which the States do find, ariſe from <hi>England,</hi> though (as we were pleaſed to ſay) we had more advantage than prejudice to expect from the alliance that his Excellency would ſay nothing of what is paſt, nor of the preſent ſtate of the one and other Kingdom; but that it was moſt certainly known that our people did deal much more with <hi>Erance</hi> than with <hi>England,</hi> and that in their Commerce they were far more ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>villy uſed in <hi>France</hi> than in <hi>England;</hi> and that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> did manage their Trade by their own Natives, but the <hi>French</hi> by the <hi>Hollanders.</hi> And as we were about to diſcourſe further of this Affair, his Excellency ſeemed willing to break off; and in concluſion told us, that if your High and Mightineſſes did not within ten days after that Monſieur <hi>D' Avaux</hi> ſhould by a Memorial preſent to you, what by the King and his Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency was propoſed to us, declare that your High and Mightineſſes would renew a defenſive League with his Majeſty, there ſhould no more be ſaid of it: but that his Majeſty would forthwith reſolve on what ſhould be thought moſt expedient for advancing the Intereſt of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; and that whatever might happen upon it, that matters might be known, the Count <hi>D' Avaux</hi> ſhould wait on all the Members of your High and Mightineſſes Aſſemblies, and declare to them the good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions and inclinations that his Majeſty has towards them; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon we took our leave of Monſieur <hi>Colbert:</hi> and ſo remain.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="memorandum">
            <head>The Memorial preſented by the <hi>French</hi> Ambaſſadour to the States General, <hi>January 22. 1680.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe Count <hi>D' Avaux</hi> Ambaſſador extraordinary of the moſt Chriſtian King, having Advice from the King his Maſter, that his Majeſty had made a Declaration to the Ambaſſadors of your High and Mightineſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; does believe that he had not delayed a minutes time in obeying the Orders he received to acquaint your Lordſhips with the ſame.</p>
            <p>His Majeſty who on the Third of this Inſtant made known by Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>Colbert</hi> his Intentions to the Ambaſſadors of your High and Migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſſes, has now more fully explained to them himſelf his own meaning, and therefore gave your Ambaſſadors <hi>an Audience</hi> on the Fifteenth In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:98825:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>wherein his Majeſty confirmed to them all that Monſieur <hi>Colbert</hi> had formerly declared in his Name. What the ſaid Ambaſſador mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to your High and Mightineſſes in his <hi>Memorial</hi> of the Twelfth Inſtant, he will not repeat again in this; but only tell you, that his Majeſty has approved him in all that he has declared in his <hi>Memorials;</hi> and that be admired that after he had firſt mentioned his friendſhip, and ſo often te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified the ſame to your High and Mightineſſes, by the concluſion of the Peace, and the plain demonſtrations of his Majeſties ſinoere willingneſs to enter into the ſame Alliance which at other times he has had with your Lordſhips; your High and Mightineſſes ſhould ſo long protract an Affair, that for many reaſons his Majeſty knew to be ſo much to your Advantage. That your preſent proceedings did not at all correſpond to the Zeal which your High and Mightineſſes made in the year 1662. to renew with his Maſter the Alliance that then was concluded. That his Majeſty knew not what to attribute to ſo conſiderable a Difference, and that he could not conceive why your High and Mightineſſes will not re-enter into the ſame Engagement and Confederacy, but make difficulties in a matter, which if not ſpeedily concluded, as it has been propoſed, his Majeſty ſhould have cauſe to believe that the States have altered their meaſures. His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty deſired that your High and Mightineſſes would give him your Anſwer by the expreſs Courrier whom his Majeſty reſolved to ſend to his Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour here, and his intention being to have a ſpeedy reſolution in this Affair, he expected that your High and Mightineſſes would give the ſame, according as he had acquainted your Ambaſſadors, who promiſed to procure it. As the Courrier was ready to depart, his Majeſty being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed of what had paſſed here, called your Ambaſſadour again to Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience on the Sixteenth Inſtant, telling them that he could not ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently expreſs his wonder of the manner how in <hi>Holland</hi> they had treated the ſubject of the propoſed Alliance, that the Declaration which the Penſionary <hi>Fagell</hi> made to his Ambaſſador, of the States unwillingneſs to enter into any Alliance with his Majeſty upon fear that it might be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicial to the eſtabliſhed Peace, was ſo far from pleaſing him, that he had ordered his Ambaſſadour to refuſe the ſame Alliance; and that he ſhould viſit all the Deputies of the States, and acquaint them with his Majeſties Intentions. That he was willing your High and Mightineſſes ſhould know ſo much; and that he had charged his Ambaſſador to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect now a final concluſion of this Affair, and that hereafter it was his will that his Ambaſſador ſhould ſpeak no more of the Matter, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive any publick Act concerning it: And that conſequently your High and Mightineſſes ought to expect that his Majeſty would enter into any Alliances which might be propoſed to him for the welfare of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and that he would induſtriouſly comply with the ways which were daily offered for promoting the Commerce of his Subjects. That his Majeſty knew not how to threaten the States with his Indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; but that his diſpleaſure upon the account of theſe their proceedings, might do them more prejudice than the Menaces of others. That his Majeſty has enjoyned your Ambaſſadours to ſignifie to your High and Mightineſſes what he told them; and that they ſhould take care not to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his ſenſe, as had been done in ſome Matters of great Importance which
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:98825:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>his Majeſty was acquainted with, within eight hours after, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in his Majeſty had charged Mr. <hi>Colbert</hi> to explain his meaning. Upon concluſion of the Audience, his Majeſty told your Ambaſſadors that they ſhould repair to Monſieur <hi>Colbert;</hi> and that he was ſurprized, that they had Letters in <hi>Holland,</hi> ſignifying, that in caſe they would not enter into the Alliance, his Majeſty would have no reſpect to the Peace: And that they ſhould loſe their Trade; which was a miſconſtruction of his ſenſe, wherewith his Majeſty was diſpleaſed; and that they ſhould only take into conſideration that what had paſt within eight or ten days, might in the beginning have been thought a juſt ground of his Majeſties diſſatisfaction at their proceedings.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Datum Hague</hi> 
                  <date>22. <hi>Jan.</hi> 1680.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="memorandum">
            <head>The Memorial of Mr. <hi>Sidney,</hi> Envoy extraordinary of the King of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> to the States General of the <hi>United Provinces,</hi> the <hi>23.</hi> of <hi>Jan. 1680.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe ſubſcribed Envoy extraordinary of the King of Great <hi>Britain,</hi> ſeeing by the Memorial which the Ambaſſador of <hi>France</hi> preſented yeſterday to your Lordſhips, that he continues by urgent Inſtances to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce your Lordſhips to enter into that Defenſive League which the moſt Chriſtian King propoſed to your Lordſhips ſometime ſince, he finds him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf obliged by new Orders from the King his Maſter, to renew the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances by him made to your Lordſhips, by his Memorial of the Ninth Inſtant, that you will not enter into ſuch a Treaty as the King his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter cannot take to be other than an engagement againſt his Majeſty, who pretends not to uſe ſuch Menaces as the Memorials of the <hi>French</hi> Ambaſſadour are filled with; although the King his Maſter hath more cauſe to complain, that your Lordſhips have but even now paſſed the Act of Guarranty, to which your Lordſhips were obliged by two ſuch ſolemn Treaties. But as his Majeſty takes nothing more to heart than the advantage of this Republick, ſo he will not preſs them upon any thing that is not for their conveniency and intereſt.</p>
            <p>The King his Maſter perſwades himſelf alſo, that after all thoſe Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances of his Amity and Aſſiſtance in what ever may happen, which he hath given your Ambaſſador at his Court, whereof without all doubt he hath informed your Lordſhips, you will not make an Alliance, which he cannot judge to be other than againſt himſelf; and that the Inſtances of the moſt Chriſtian King, though too preſſing and importunate to be preſented to a free Commonwealth, will not be capable to divert your Lordſhips from your true Intereſt, nor from the Amity and ſtrict Union that is between his Majeſty and this State, in a time and on an occaſion when he gives your Lordſhips ſo eſſential marks, and when your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips have aſſured his Majeſty that you will continue and encreaſe the ſame on your parts.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Given at the <hi>Hague,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Jan.</hi> 23. 1680.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Sidney.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:98825:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Conſiderations</hi> touching the Alliance with <hi>France.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe King of <hi>France</hi> being deſirous to renew an Alliance with the States, hath ſolicited the ſame by his Ambaſſadors; and His Majeſty has reaſon to believe that the States will accept of an Offer ſo advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geous to them, when upon that account he is willing to comply with them therein for theſe <hi>Conſiderations:</hi> That the States have renewed their Alliance with all thoſe Princes with whom they have been in War: That they have not only after the Peace concluded with <hi>England,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed their Alliance with that Crown, but made a new one beſides: That in the ſame Treaty by which they made Peace with <hi>Sweden,</hi> they renewed their former Treaties of Alliance: That the King of <hi>France</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires no more of the States but the ſame thing; and if this be not granted, his Majeſty will have reaſon to believe that the States have particular Reaſons that oblige them to contract no nearer Alliance or Friendſhip with him, and whether his Majeſty in that caſe will not be obliged to take his meaſures accordingly. And ſeeing the States are in Alliance with all the Princes of <hi>Europe,</hi> except the King of <hi>France,</hi> with whom they will make none, whether his Majeſty may not juſtly belief that thoſe En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements which they have with other Princes, tend to the concerting of Meaſures againſt him, when ever opportunity ſhall offer: That it is no excuſe to ſay, that the Alliance which the States have with <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Spain</hi> were made during the War, ſeeing the Alliance propoſed by <hi>France</hi> does not contain any ſpecial Engagement, and indeed no other but the ſame Conditions which were deſired by the States in 1662. If in the preſent Conjuncture the renewing of ſuch an Alliance be refuſed, his Majeſty is obliged to believe that the Intereſt of <hi>France</hi> is not conſidered, and that the Intereſt of the States is inconſiſtent with it; and by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, whether he may not always for the future take other Meaſures; becauſe the States by their refuſal will make appear that it is never their Intereſt to ally with <hi>France:</hi> That if it be ſaid, that though the Alliance be good and advantageous, yet that the concluſion thereof ought to be deferred till another time; whether if his Majeſty did not know (which he does know) what the reaſons of this delay were, he ought not to believe that they ſeek to defer the Alliance only becauſe they never in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to conclude it. And whether thoſe Reaſons (let them be what they will) will not be the very ſame ſix Months, or a year hence. And whether ever it will be found expedient to renew the Alliance between <hi>France</hi> and this State, till the Complaints that any Princes may make againſt the renewing of the ſaid Alliance begin to be ſuſpected by the States. If a Prince (let him be who he will) ſhould oppoſe the States making of a defenſive Alliance, and innocent Amity; yea ſuch an one
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:98825:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>as he has with them himſelf already, whether he does not thereby ſhow that he intends to attack the one or the other, and that he has private deſigns of his own. That <hi>France</hi> is far from taking it ill that the States ſhould procure themſelves new Friends and Alliances; His Majeſty being ready to obtain the ſame for them, if he knew of any Prince who was not already in League with them. That there is no reaſon to excuſe the renewing of the Alliance with <hi>France,</hi> becauſe they refuſed to enter into the League of <hi>Guarantee</hi> with <hi>England,</hi> becauſe the ſaid League was as plainly intended againſt <hi>France,</hi> as the triple Alliance was formerly. That there is no equality between making a League of this nature with a Prince with whom they are allied already, and the renewing of an Alliance betwixt the States and a Prince with whom they are not allied, and with whom they have always heretofore been ſo nearly engaged. If there be any good ground to ſay, That the States ought to remain Neuter, and not to do that for one Prince, which they have refuſed to another; whether their entering into a nearer Alliance with one Prince during the War, and their refuſing to renew an Alliance with another after the Peace, be good ſigns of Neutrality. That if the Treaties, which the States have made during the War, do hinder them to renew the Alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with <hi>France,</hi> it doth appear to His Majeſty, that the ſame Spirit which bore they ſway againſt him during the War, doth ſtill oppoſe him ſince the Peace. Whether His Majeſty ought not to believe, that the States have not ſo faithfully performed their part, as he hath ſincerely reſtored them to his friendſhip, ſeeing they refuſe to give him the ſame Tokens of Affection which His Majeſty doth offer them, and which they formerly with ſo much Zeal wiſhed for. That if the ground of His Majeſty's deſire be conſidered, it will be found, that they are punctually obliged to ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill the ſame, becauſe the King's Letter of the <hi>18th</hi> of <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> 1678. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained not the propoſals of a Peace which they liked ſo well, but upon condition they ſhould enter into the old Alliance and Confederacy which they formerly had with His Majeſty. That though the King of <hi>France</hi> had no reaſon to fear, but that His Forces ſhould not be power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful enough to defend himſelf againſt the Enterpriſes of theſe who are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>affected towards him, yet he thinks it concerns him once for all to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed of the ſentiments they have in regard of him, as he is already ſufficiently of the ill intentions of thoſe who oppoſe the renovation of the Alliance, becauſe they cannot without envy or fear look upon the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages of this Union. That it is with little ground ſaid by ſome, that the States never made Alliance without preſſing Reaſons, ſuch as thoſe which made them contract with other Princes during the laſt War, and that theſe Alliances were not to continue after the Peace. Such as are better infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of the State of Affairs, do well know, that the Alliance of <hi>France</hi> was not made upon the account of any particular Caſe or Occurrence, but upon the deſire of the States during the Peace: And that indeed the Alliances which they have made with other Princes, do alſo continue ſince the War, ſome for 20, ſome for 30 years, and ſome for ever; and <hi>France</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the only Crown with which the States will not treat, an eaſie Anſwer may be given to what ſome publicly ſay here, That the Alliance is indeed very
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:98825:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>advantagious, but that the States at leaſt ought to take their own time, when they ſhall think it moſt convenient.</p>
            <p>To this it may be ſaid, that it will be agreed, that if the States them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves would propoſe a new Alliance, it would be juſt that they ſhould ſet ſuch a time for the concluding of it as they might think convenient: But ſince His Moſt Chriſtian Majeſty deſires them to renew the former Allian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces they have had with him, and that it doth not come from them, they muſt have other regards, which they conſider more than the advantage of His Majeſty's Amity.</p>
            <p>That if this matter be rightly conſidered, it may be ſaid, that a lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger time hath been allowed than was neceſſary for to determin themſelves ſince the firſt mention of this Alliance, a Miniſter of the Court of <hi>France</hi> having made a propoſal of it in my laſt.</p>
            <p>That the King of <hi>France</hi> may preſume, that the States are ſo wiſe in diſcerning their own intereſt, and ſo kind to it, as to have conſidered ſince my laſt, what they were to do in relation to this Propoſal. That his Ambaſſadour having afterward renewed the ſame, His Majeſty may have reaſon, if it be not anſwered, to ſuſpect them, and to demand their peremptory Anſwer, that ſo he may once for all take his meaſures accordingly. That the King of <hi>France</hi> cannot but take it ill, that the States ſhould refuſe to enter into this Alliance, out of fear of diſobliging thoſe, who, without any reaſon, oppoſe the ſame, and upon no other deſign, but to conclude a League offenſive againſt him, that being the only reaſon why they endeavour to hinder this defenſive Alliance.</p>
            <p>It is to be preſumed, that the King of <hi>France</hi> will not always accept of what the States ſhall be pleaſed to reſolve upon; and after ſo many advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages of Amity which he has offered to them, they muſt thank themſelves, if, when he ſees his Alliance refuſed, His Majeſty do take ſuch meaſures as will not be very agreeable to them.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:98825:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Reflexions</hi> on the <hi>Conſiderations,</hi> touching the Memorials delivered to their <hi>High</hi> and <hi>Mighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes</hi> by the Count <hi>d' Avaux,</hi> on the <hi>12<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>22<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
               </hi> of <hi>January, 1680.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE ſubſtance of theſe Conſiderations may be divided, either into Motives, to induce the States to enter into an Alliance with <hi>France,</hi> or Anſwers to the Reaſons the States alleage, for refuſing the ſame.</p>
            <p>The Motives are theſe three following: 1. That the States have made Alliances with other Princes and States. 2 That they are obliged to make an Alliance with the King of <hi>France,</hi> becauſe they accepted the Letter of the <hi>18th</hi> of <hi>May,</hi> 1678. 3. Becauſe that the King, in caſe that the Alliance do not take effect, will have cauſe, in regard of the carriage of the States towards him, to reſent it to their prejudice, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently take ſuch meaſures as will be very unpleaſing to them.</p>
            <p>As to the firſt; there needs not much debate, but that the Alliance which a State does make with ſome Princes, doth not oblige them to enter into the ſame with others; and that the ſame may be refuſed without any ill inclination, and much more without any intention never to enter into an Alliance with the Party with whom they refuſe it at preſent. All free States muſt have a freedom to judge of their Intereſts, which do vary according to the different conjunctures of time; and the juſt fear which the States have, (above other conſiderations) that they may be drawn into a War by this defenſive Alliance with <hi>France,</hi> muſt plainly declare the innocency of their deſires which they have to refuſe the ſame. It is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to be obſerved, that it is true that the Alliances with <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Spain</hi> were concluded during the War, which evidently demonſtrates, that they have not been made out of compliance to one or other Prince; and that the States cannot diſcharge themſelves of them.</p>
            <p>Concerning the ſecond: It is to be admired that the Author of thoſe Conſiderations ſhould poſitively avert, that the States are obliged to enter into an Alliance with <hi>France,</hi> by reaſon of a Letter he mentions. The Moſt Chriſtian King doth not ſpeak any thing in that Letter of renewing the Alliance, as a condition on which he will make Peace, but is willing to free the States of thoſe fears which they had, that if the <hi>Spaniards</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in War, he would make himſelf Maſter of all the <hi>Neatherlands;</hi> and therefore promiſes, that in caſe <hi>Spain</hi> would not accept of a Peace, after the States had made one, and were again entred into their old Alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with him, that he would always maintain the propoſed Frontiers, and attack none of the places therein contained. Now ſince <hi>Spain</hi> did accept of Peace, there was no occaſion for the Contents of the latter. The King of <hi>France</hi> is by the ſaid Peace obliged to leave the Frontiers in the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:98825:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>conditioned State, and the States are not obliged to re-enter into an Alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance which is now deſired of them.</p>
            <p>As to the third Motive. As the States may refuſe the Alliance with the Moſt Chriſtian King, without having any ill intention againſt him, ſo he has reaſon to be ſatisfied, and not deal with them as ſuch who are other ways affected towards him, when with reſpect they purge themſelves, and give aſſurances, that they will religiouſly preſerve the Peace with him. If the King be juſt, he will not break his Peace with him; if generous, he will not reckon their deſires of maintaining their freedom entire, as a piece of ill conduct in them; and will not encreale their jealouſies, that he has a deſign abſolutely to diſpoſe of them, and to make their State a Ladder, whereby to climb up to a Lording it over all <hi>Europe,</hi> and that under pretext of ſhewing them Tokens of their Amity.</p>
            <p>Upon the Anſwers, which the Author of theſe Conſiderations do make to excuſe the States from entering into an Alliance, theſe following Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flexions may be made. Firſt, in regard he queſtions, whether the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints, which ſeveral Princes may make concerning the renewing of the ſaid Alliance, muſt not be ſuſpected. It is not with more reaſon to be queſtioned (as has been touched before) whether the great heat, with which the Moſt Chriſtian King doth ſue the ſaid Alliance, doth not make him ſuſpected of his willingneſs to break the Peace ſo lately re-eſtabliſhed in <hi>Europe,</hi> and for the maintenance of which the States have ſo great an Intereſt. That there is not the leaſt appearance, that any of thoſe Princes who oppoſes the ſaid Alliance, does the ſame with any intention to attack the Moſt Chriſtian King.</p>
            <p>And ſeeing His Moſt Chriſtian Majeſty has no cauſe to fear that his power ſhould not be ſufficient to defend himſelf; what important reaſon can he have to oblige the States to a defenſive Alliance, unleſs he has a deſign to attack ſome of his Neighbours, who for the ſame reaſons juſtly oppoſe the Concluſion of the ſaid Alliance, though they do it not with threantings of their Indignation, which <hi>France</hi> uſes to force and preſs the ſame.</p>
            <p>That, with good ground may be alleaged againſt the ſaid Alliance, the refuſal which the States have made of entering with <hi>England</hi> into an Alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of <hi>Gnarantee,</hi> though it was their greateſt intereſt to make the ſame, as being thereunto obliged; and ſeeing they have not refuſed it, but only in deference to His Moſt Chriſtian Majeſty, and that the ſaid Alliance was not expreſly propoſed againſt him, but againſt the party who ſhould break the Peace.</p>
            <p>The reſt of the Conſiderations relate chiefly to the time in which it is deſired the Alliance ſhould be concluded, and it ſeems ſuperfluous to debate that, before one knows for certain whether it will be advantagious to make the ſame, or not.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:98825:11"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
